Guide to the George A. Dudley Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George A. Dudley papers
1948-2005
MS 1861
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
58.25
(46 boxes)
The papers are comprised of writings, drafts, research and topical files, notes, correspondence, clippings, articles, reports, proposals, and other documents relating to the career of architect and planner George A. Dudley, who oversaw the development and construction of many large-scale projects, such as campuses for the State University of New York and mass housing programs in Latin America, the Middle East, and India. The collection includes records produced and collected by Dudley when he worked both domestically and internationally as an architect, planner, administrator, and consultant, as well as materials relating to Dudley's book, A Workshop for Peace: Designing the United Nations Headquarters (1994), based on Dudley's experience in 1947 working on the U.N. Headquarters under architect Wallace K. Harrison.
Dudley, George A.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
George Austin Dudley, born in Pittsburgh on December 24, 1914, attended Yale University, earning a Bachelor of Arts in 1936, Bachelor of Fine Arts in Architecture in 1938, and Master of Fine Arts in Urban Planning in 1940. Early in his career as an architect, Dudley worked under Wallace K. Harrison on the planning and construction of the United Nations Headquarters in New York City – an experience he later recounted in his book A Workshop for Peace: Designing the United Nations Headquarters (1994). Other large-scale planning projects on which Dudley worked with Harrison are Rockefeller Center, Lincoln Center, and the Empire State Plaza in Albany, New York.
Dudley continued to focus on complex building projects for institutional clients—both governmental and academic—throughout his long career, working both domestically and abroad. From 1948 to 1960, Dudley served as president of the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Housing Corporation, which constructed thousands of units of government-financed, low-cost modular housing in Latin America, the Middle East, and India. In the early 1960s, Dudley headed the State University Construction Fund, New York, overseeing the financing, planning, and building of several SUNY campuses, including Stony Brook, New Paltz, and Buffalo. Dudley was founding dean, from 1965 to 1967, of the School of Architecture and Urban Planning at the University of California, Los Angeles, and he also served as dean of the School of Architecture at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. In the late 1970s and 1980s, Dudley acted as a consultant on several planning and development projects in Asia, the Middle East, and the U.S.
Dudley died in Rensselaerville, New York, in February 2005.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Barbara C.M. Dudley and George B. Dudley 2005.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The papers are comprised of writings, drafts, research and topical files, notes, correspondence, clippings, articles, reports, proposals, and other materials. Documents remain in their original folders and their arrangement has not been altered since the collection was acquired. Descriptions are transcribed from original handwritten folder titles, and materials relating to a specific project or topic may be housed in multiple, non-consecutive boxes and folders.
The papers extend over two accessions. The original accession consists largely of materials relating to Dudley's book, A Workshop for Peace: Designing the United Nations Headquarters, published in 1994. Accession 2006-M-026 comprises documents produced and collected over the course of Dudley's career as an architect, planner, administrator, and consultant working both domestically and internationally.
Building -- Planning; City planning; Housing; Dudley, George A.; Maʻhad al-Kuwayt lil-Abḥāth al-ʻIlmīyah; International Basic Economy Corporation; State University of New York; United Nations ( Headquarters)
- Original accession
  - Loose notes and photographs (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Part III. Space and functional requirements (Box 1)
  - Delegations building (Box 1)
  - Specialized agencies (Box 1)
  - UN housing, school for UN children (Box 1)
  - Secretariat (Box 1)
  - General Assembly (Box 1)
  - Council chambers design; Conference building (Box 1)
  - Housing Authority building (Box 1)
  - Submission and publication of report (Box 1)
  - Report to Secretary-General (Box 1)
  - Part V. Headquarters Planning Office (Box 1)
  - Draft design and model (Box 1)
  - Part VI. Work of the Planning Office (Box 1)
  - July-December 1947 (Box 1)
  - Development around site (Box 1)
  - 1950-1951, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Dedication and occupancy (Box 1)
  - Part VII. Construction (Box 1)
  - Part VIII. In Retrospect (Box 1)
  - Works of art, gifts (Box 1)
  - Changes and additions (Box 1)
  - Occupation experience (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970 building project (Box 1)
  - Worksheets and meeting attendance (Box 1)
  - Appendix B (Box 1)
  - Appendix on Le Corbusier (Box 1)
  - Cast of characters (Box 1)
  - Chapter drafts, clippings, documents and copies of documents (Box 2–3)
  - Subject files (Box 3)
  - Corbusier (Box 3)
  - Abramovitz, Max (Box 4)
  - Allen, William (Box 4)
  - Asplund, Hans (Box 4)
  - Backroom Boys (Box 4)
  - Basson, Nikolai D. (Box 4)
  - Belgium (Box 4)
  - Bodiansky, Vladimir (Box 4)
  - Brunfaut, Gaston (Box 4)
  - Century Association (Box 4)
  - Chambellin, Rene (Box 4)
  - Churchill, Winston (Box 4)
  - Cormier, Ernest (Box 4)
  - Engineers (Box 4)
  - Ferriss, Hugh (Box 4)
  - Harrison, Wallace K. (Box 4)
  - Havlicek, Josef (Box 4)
  - Ingersoll, Richard (Box 4)
  - Johnson, Philip (Box 4)
  - Lane, Barbara (Box 4)
  - Le Corbusier -[see Box 3] (Box 4)
  - Liang Ssu-Cheng (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Lie, Trygvie (Box 4)
  - Markelius, Sven (Box 4)
  - Moses, Robert (Box 4)
  - Mumford, Lewis (Box 4)
  - Niemeyer, Oscar (Box 4)
  - Nitzchke, Oscar (Box 4)
  - Nivola (Box 4)
  - Nowicki, Matthew (Box 4)
  - Pontabry, Robert J. (Box 4)
  - Robertson, Howard (Box 4)
  - Rockefellers (Box 4)
  - Shaw, Arvin (Box 4)
  - Soilleux, G.A. (Box 4)
  - Skidmore - Bunshaft (Box 4)
  - Vilamajo, Julio (Box 4)
  - Walker, Ralph (Box 4)
  - Weisman, Ernest (Box 4)
  - Zeckendorff, William (Box 4)
  - Notes and drafts on individual meetings (Box 5)
  - Drafts and notes (Box 5)
  - Title page (Box 5)
  - Prospectus (Box 5)
  - Acknowledgements and sources (Box 5)
  - Preface (Box 5)
  - Introduction (Box 5)
  - Prior to Board of Design (Box 5)
  - February 1947 (Box 5)
  - Headquarters Advisory Committee and Planning Office (Box 5)
  - Meetings of Board of Design and of Headquarters Advisory Committee -drafts and notes (Box 5)
  - Harrison and Abramovitz -Minutes of Design Meetings (Box 5)
  - Financing agreement (Box 5)
  - Board of Design after June 9, 1947 meeting (Box 5)
  - Dispersal of Design Board (Box 5)
  - General Assembly session, Paris, 1948 (Box 5)
  - Cornerstone ceremony, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
  - Theory, Threads (Box 5)
  - Ted [Gachot] (Box 6)
  - Notes and drafts (Box 6)
  - Yale Press (Box 6)
  - Architectural History Foundation (Box 6)
  - National Endowment for the Arts (Box 6)
  - Site search (Box 6)
  - New Yorker profile of Corbusier (Box 6)
  - Publication prospectus (Box 6)
  - Notes on Glenn E. Bennett diary (Box 6)
  - Carlson, Eric (Box 6)
  - Cohen, Stephen (Box 6)
  - Goldberger, Paul (Box 6)
  - Harris, Michael M. (Box 6)
  - Huxtable, Ada Louise (Box 6)
  - Nelson Rockefeller book (Box 6)
  - Letters to embassies (Box 6)
  - Architectural History Foundation (Box 6)
  - Christy, Arthur H. (Box 6)
  - Le Corbusier (Box 6)
  - Le Corbusier Foundation (Box 6)
  - Sorenson, Abel and Peter (Box 6)
  - U.N. Plaque (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and notes (Box 7)
  - U.N. exhibit, Albany Library (Box 7)
  - X-City (Box 7)
  - UN brochures (Box 7)
  - A Workshop for Peace-galleys(?) (Box 7)
  - Transparencies (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Drafts on meetings (Box 7)
  - Handwritten and printed drafts (Box 8)
  - Johnson, Philip (Box 9)
  - Museum of Modern Art: The U.N. in Perspective (Box 9)
  - Loose papers (Box 9)
  - Phipps, chapter 3 (Box 9)
  - Loose papers and publications (Box 9)
  - Proposed UN architecture exhibit (Box 9)
  - Loose papers and publications, many personal (Box 9)
  - Abu Nuwaz Development Project, proposal, 1981 April (Box 9)
  - Saudi Arabia National Center for Science and Technology, proposal, 1981 October 15 (Box 9)
  - Kuwait Institute for Scientific Research, Environmental Planning System, environmental base document, 1978 February (Box 9)
  - University of Hong Kong, Department of Architecture (Box 9)
  - Tsuen Wan New Town Development Office, topogrpahical maps, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Efectos de la instalacion de una industria siderurgica en la ciudad de maracaibo, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Urbis Planning Design Group (Box 9)
  - State Mosque competition, Baghdad, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Loose articles (Box 9)
  - CNN (Box 9)
  - Loose correspondence and papers (Box 9)
  - Clippings and notes re Rockefeller Center (Box 9)
  - Photographs of old New York maps (Box 9)
  - AWFP-incoming letters and comments (Box 9)
  - Bryn Mawr Library (Box 9)
  - Rockefeller Center (Box 9)
  - Le Vieux Port de Montreal (Box 9)
  - U.N.: Proposed Office Building for Delegations and Specialized Agencies (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous architecture publications, magazines, and project brochures (Box 10)
  - Reprints of articles on UN (Box 10)
  - Harrison, Wallace K. (Box 10)
  - Drafts and notes (Box 10)
  - Original notes and drawings taken by Dudley at Board of Design meetings (Box 10)
  - Meetings 1-6 (Box 10)
  - Typed drafts of meeting notes (Box 11)
  - Notes and sketches: original, photocopies, and photographs (Box 11)
  - Typed drafts of meeting notes (Box 12)
  - Schedules for AWFP (Box 12)
  - Index binder (Box 12)
  - UN photo list (Box 12)
  - Sorenson and Dudley draft (Box 12)
  - Typed drafts of meeting notes (Box 13)
  - Draft introduction (Box 13)
  - Binder with original notes (Box 13)
  - Proposals for UN Headquarters (Box 14)
  - San Francisco (Box 14)
  - Boston (Box 14)
  - St. Louis (Box 14)
  - Blue Hills, Massachusetts (Box 14)
  - Easton, New York (Box 14)
  - Westchester-Fairfield (Box 14)
  - Niagara Falls (Box 14)
  - Philadelphia (Box 14)
  - Kuwait Institute for Scientific Research, Environmental Planning System (Box 14)
  - Lloyd Site Master Development Plan, 1975 (Box 14)
  - IBEC housing, El Salvador, 1952 (Box 14)
  - University of Miami, Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Science. Master plan, 1979 (Box 14)
  - 270 Park Avenue (Box 14)
  - Drafts and documents (Box 15)
  - Drafts and copies of documents (Box 16)
  - Snapshots from Board of Design (Box 16)
  - Proposal to facilitate the expansion of the headquarters of the United Nations, 1968 (Box 16)
  - Drafts and copies of documents (Box 17)
  - Report to the General Assembly of the United Nations by the Secretary-General on the Permanent Headquarters of the United Nations (copies in multiple languages), 1947 (Box 17)
  - Report of the Headquarters Commission to the second Part of the First Session of the General Assembly of the United Nations, 1946 (Box 17)
  - Engineering and Technical Studies of the Headquarters Planning Office, 1947 (Box 17)
  - Photocopies and photocopies from various repositories (Box 18)
  - Saudi Arabia National Center for Science and Technology, Science Hall Design Report (Box 19)
  - State Mosque, Baghdad (Box 19)
  - Binder with materials relating to the publication of A Workshop for Peace (Box 20)
- Additional material, Accession 2006-M-026
  - A Workshop for Peace -post-publication files (Box 1)
  - Dudley's Drawings-files (Box 2)
  - Rensselaerville and local files (Box 3)
  - New York State
    - New York State: State University Construction Fund-reports, notes (Box 4)
    - New York State
      - Development plans (Box 5)
      - Environmental Facilities Corporation (Box 5)
    - Albany, New York, planning (Box 5)
    - Albany, New York, planning (Box 6)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson-architectural records project (Box 7)
    - Architectural archives (Box 7)
    - New York State
      - Building programs (Box 7)
      - Office buildings (Box 7)
    - Rockefeller, David (Box 7)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson (Box 7)
    - Rockefeller Brothers Fund, Rockefeller Family Fund (Box 7)
    - Rockefeller, Winthrop (Box 7)
    - South Mall (Box 7)
    - Albany (Box 8)
  - Alphabetical files: includes correspendence, clippings, articles
    - Aalto (Box 9)
    - AGA (Adinolfi, Anthony G.) (Box 9)
    - Beinecke, Bill (Box 9)
    - Barnes, Edward Larrabee (Box 9)
    - Chadirji, Rifat (Box 9)
    - Christ-Janer, Victor (Box 9)
    - Dykes, Gordon W. (Box 9)
    - Harrison, Wallace K. (Box 9)
    - Hayes, David (Box 9)
    - Johnson, Philip (Box 9)
    - Koolhaas, Rem (Box 9)
    - Liu Urban Design Associates (Box 9)
    - Moore, Vincent J. (Box 9)
    - Neutra (Box 9)
    - Pei, I.M. (Box 9)
    - Pelli, Cesar (Box 9)
    - Rockefellers (Box 9)
    - Stern, Robert A.M. (Box 9)
    - Sutnar (Box 9)
    - Tafel, Edgar (Box 9)
    - Venturi (Box 9)
    - Wright, Frank Lloyd, Foundation (Box 9)
  - Loose articles and reports (Box 9)
  - Habitat reports (end of box 7) (Box 10)
  - Alphabetical files of correspondence with individuals (beginning of box 16) (Box 10)
  - Appointment book (end of box 16), 1974 (Box 11)
  - Chronological correspondence files (begin box 1) (Box 11)
  - Post-War Connecticut reports (Box 11)
  - UCLA files (includes UC Berkeley, California Polytechnic State University) (Box 11)
  - IBEC housing (Box 12)
    - Additional material (Box 13)
  - Middle East
    - Saudi Arabia (Box 14)
    - Iraq (Box 14)
    - Middle East (Box 14)
    - Saudi Arabia (Box 14)
    - Saudi Consultant/Educational Planning and Development Consortium - Islamic University (Box 14)
    - Saudi Consultant/Educational Planning and Development Consortium - Joint Ventures Consultants (Box 14)
    - Saudi Arabia (Box 14)
    - Iraq
      - Al Karkh (Box 15)
      - Abu Nuwas (Box 15)
    - Aga Khan Award for Architecture (Box 15)
    - Kuwait Institute for Scientific Research (Box 15)
    - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (Box 15)
    - Saudi Arabian National Center for Science and Technology (Box 16)
    - Saudi Arabian National Center for Science and Technology (Box 17)
    - Kuwait Institute for Scientific Research (Box 18)
    - Iraq State Mosque, King Abdullahaziz University, Islamic Development Bank (Box 19)
      - Additional material (Box 20)
    - Abu Nuwas (Box 21)
      - Additional material (Box 22)
    - Saudi Arabia (Box 23)
  - Venezuela (Box 24)
  - Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute (Box 24)
  - Galapagos, Peru, and Ecuador (Box 24)
  - Trinidad-Tobago (Box 24)
  - Uruguay (Box 24)
  - Panama (Box 24)
  - Mexico (Box 24)
  - Nicaragua (Box 24)
  - Jamaica (Box 24)
  - Honduras (Box 24)
  - Guatemala (Box 24)
  - Guyana (Box 24)
  - Haiti (Box 24)
  - Ecuador, Galapagos (Box 24)
  - Dominican Republic (Box 24)
  - Cuba (Box 24)
  - Costa Rica (Box 24)
  - Oman (Box 24)
  - Portugal (Box 24)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 24)
  - Russia (Box 24)
  - Scandinavia (Box 24)
  - Scotland (Box 24)
  - Spain (Box 24)
  - Barcelona (Box 24)
  - Switzerland (Box 24)
  - Turkey (Box 24)
  - Yugoslavia (Box 24)
  - New York State (Box 24)
  - Brazil (Box 24)
  - Columbia (Box 25)
  - Iraq (Box 25)
  - Bahrain (Box 25)
  - Iran (Box 25)
  - Jordan (Box 25)
  - Kuwait (Box 25)
  - Lebanon (Box 25)
  - Norway (Box 25)
  - Oman (Box 25)
  - Tunis (Box 25)
  - Gulf States (Box 25)
  - China (Box 26)
  - Bangladesh (Box 26)
  - Afghanistan (Box 26)
  - Hong Kong (Box 26)
  - India (Box 26)
  - India and Pakistan (Box 27)
  - Indonesia (Box 27)
  - Japan (Box 27)
  - Korea (Box 27)
  - Philippines (Box 27)
  - Singapore (Box 27)
  - Sri Lanka (Box 27)
  - Thailand (Box 27)
  - Australia (Box 27)
  - Belize (Box 27)
  - United States-Boston, Cambridge, Newport (Box 27)
  - Africa (Box 27)
  - Alaska (Box 27)
  - Canada (Box 27)
  - Cyprus (Box 27)
  - Denmark (Box 27)
  - Egypt (Box 27)
  - England (Box 27)
  - Germany (Box 27)
  - Greece and Turkey (Box 27)
  - Hawaii (Box 27)
  - Holland (Box 27)
  - India (Box 27)
  - Ireland (Box 27)
  - Italy (Box 27)
  - Jordan (Box 27)
  - Kenya (Box 27)
  - Lebanon (Box 27)
  - Malaysia (Box 27)
  - Malta (Box 27)
  - Mediterranean-Minorca, Maillorca (Box 27)
  - Conference proceedings, reports (Box 28)
  - Conference proceedings, reports (Box 29)
  - Reference files, speeches, small projects
    - China (Box 30)
    - United Nations Habitat (Box 30)
    - Society for College and University Planning (Box 30)
    - International Design Conference, Aspen, Colorado, 1969 (Box 30)
    - Ditchley Foundation (Box 30)
    - New Towns (Box 30)
    - National Policy Task Force; National growth policy planning (Box 30)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson: Domestic Council (Box 30)
    - Agency for International Development (Box 30)
    - The World Bank (Box 30)
    - Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies (Box 30)
    - Progressive Architecture awards; IBEC housing; New York State symposium, Sterling Forest, 1961 (Box 30)
    - South Mall, Albany, New York (Box 30)
    - New York State Council on Architecture (Box 30)
    - Federal Public Works Employment Act (Box 30)
    - New York State Environmental Facilities Corporation (Box 31)
    - Amman and Whitney, Kunstadt Associates (Box 31)
    - Unidentified proposal drawings (Box 31)
    - Brown, Daltas and Associates (Box 31)
    - Consulting-Tafel, Erdman (Box 31)
    - Smithsonian (Box 31)
    - Consulting-Murrock (Box 31)
    - New York City/American Institute of Architects (Box 31)
    - New York State Association of Architects/American Institute of Architects (Box 31)
    - American Institute of Architects -national committees (Box 31)
    - American Institute of Architects Foundation (Box 31)
    - Federal Design Assembly (Box 31)
    - Federal Design Guidelines (Box 31)
    - National Endowment for the Arts/National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 31)
    - Saudi Arabian National Center for Science and Technology (Box 32)
    - Rose Creek Mountain Development (Box 32)
    - Arkansas (Box 32)
    - Reports and brochures (Box 32)
    - Reference, speeches, minor projects, proposals, proceeding, reports (Box 33–38)
    - Drawings for South Mall, Albany, New York (Box 39)
    - Matthew Nowicki drawings for United Nations headquarters (Box 39)
    - Unidentified drawings of United nations headquarters (Box 39)
  - Oversized
    - Iraq/Abu Nawas Conservatory Development Project
      - Report 1.1, 1981 November 27 (Box 40)
      - Report 1.2, 1982 February 25 (Box 40)
      - Report 1.3, 1982 July 31 (Box 40)
      - Report 2, 1982 January 13 (Box 40)
      - Report 3, 1982 June 15 (Box 40)
      - Report 4, 1982 April 15 (Box 40)
      - Report 5, management recommendations, two copies, one annotated rough draft, undated (Box 40)
      - Report 6.1, conceptual basis, undated (Box 40)
      - Urban design summary, two copies, 1982 (Box 40)
    - Saudi Arabia
      - Al Batin Military City master plan, site development plans, 1975 April 30 (Box 41)
      - King Khalid Military City master plan, site development plans, 1976 June (Box 41)
      - King Abdulaziz University campus project, appendix design report draft and sketches, 1987 May (Box 42)
      - Saudi Arabian National Center for Science and Technology, residential facilities and schools design report, undated (Box 42)
      - Islamic University of Madinah, master plan report, undated (Box 42)
      - King Abdulaziz University, three volumes of master plans and concept designs, undated (Box 43)
    - Proposal for New Town in Florida, undated (Box 44)
    - Paolo Soleri, 1969 (Box 44)
    - New York City Planning Commission, plans for New York City, each of the five boroughs, 1969 (Box 45)
  - Folio
    - "In a Sketchbook World, ADP 812, 1986-1987," Michael [Mytoller] (Box 46)
    - College at Fredonia, block study model II, I. M. Pei and Associates, Architects and Planners, undated (Box 46)
    - 3 Renderings of NY State Program re: Development of Air-rights over Piers, E. River Drive, etc., Schwartz, undated (Box 46)
    - Unidentified sketch, [Facoby], [1964] (Box 46)